Indiana Club records, 1906-1978 C464
Indiana University Archives
Indiana Club records
1906-1978
1915-1928
Indiana University Archives
Indiana Club (Indiana University)
C464
.4 cubic feet 1 box
The Indiana Club was established at Indiana University on December 9, 1904. The goal of the club was to advance the interests of the student body in the social, literary, political, and athletic realms. This collection consists of minute books, registers, a book on the history of the organization through 1915, records from the Alumni Association of the Indiana Club, and other documents.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The Indiana Club was first established at Indiana University on December 9, 1904. The club was reorganized September 29th, 1905 in an effort to resolve issues that had been problems during its first year. For example, the club had trouble obtaining regular membership and lacked a system to keep track of who was a member and who was not. The club was created to deal with political issues among student clubs, primarily due to the fact that fraternity and sorority members (the "Greeks"), had more clout in campus clubs than did those who were unaffiliated (the "barbs"), despite the fact that the latter made up the majority of the student population. It got to a point where the "barbs" had trouble getting involved with student organizations unless they could gain political support. The Indiana Club was first called the Barb Organization, but the name was changed at its first official meeting.
The aims of the club were primarily social and literary, although politics and athletics were part of it as well. Social events were held for members and friends, and literary programs highlighting original works such as plays were regularly held. Any IU student who was not a member of a fraternity or other organization that stood "as a unit socially and politically" (1905 Arbutus) were eligible for membership. The club is last mentioned in the Arbutus in 1929, and a letter to Alumni members dated June 1, 1929, states as follows:
"As for the Club itself, there is not much to tell. The members were very hopeful last fall, but with a debt of over five hundred dollars… hanging over them, they say they do not feel encouraged to get new people into the organization. … The debt, of course, will be cared for… but the Club will not go on unless the alumni express a desire to have it do so."
On November 20, 1915, the Alumni Association of the Indiana Club was organized. Regular updates on members, including marriage and birth announcements, were given. Records in this collection suggest that the Indiana Club alumni group was still in existence in 1978, but it is not known how long it existed after that.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series: Indiana Club records and Alumni Association of the Indiana Club records.
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into two series, Indiana Club records, 1906-1978 and Alumni Association of the Indiana Club records, 1915-1927. Both series are arranged alphabetically by folder heading. Items of note include letters from Cora B. Hennel, a book on the history of the Indiana Club up until 1915, and membership rosters.
Photographs and scrapbooks about the club are stored separately; consult the Archives Photographs Curator for access information.
Separated Material
Two envelopes of scrapbook pages were separated and transferred to the photograph collection. Consult the Archives Photographs Curator for further information.
Related Material
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers: 9142-9161, 1178
Provenance
Some materials were donated by Clifford M. Blowers via Prof. Newell Long and Cecilia Wahl to the University Archives, Feb. 1984. The rest of the collection was transferred from Collection C413, the Cecilia Hennel Hendricks family papers. Dr. Hendricks served as vice president of the organization in 1907, and was a member of the Anniversary Publication Committee, which published a book on the history of the Indiana Club in 1915. Her sister, Cora, served as treasurer in 1905, secretary in 1906, and as the alumni secretary.
College students --Indiana --Bloomington --Societies and clubs.; Alumni Association of the Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- Archives; Hendricks, Cecilia Hennel, 1883-1969; Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- Archives; Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- Records and correspondence; Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- History -- Sources; Alumni Association of the Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- Records and correspondence; Alumni Association of the Indiana Club (Indiana University) -- History -- Sources; Indiana University -- students -- Societies, etc. -- History -- Sources
- Indiana Club records, 1906-1928 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Registers, 1906-1928 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Club, 1902-1915 (Box 1)
  - Minutes (Box 1)
    - 1916-1919 (Box 1)
    - 1919-1920 (Box 1)
    - 1925-1926 (Box 1)
- Alumni Association of the Indiana Club records, 1915-1978 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and reports, 1915-1978 (Box 1)
  - Financial records, 1915-1927 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1915-1927 (Box 1)